Associated Industries of New York State / The Business Council of New York State; Records apap043
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Associated Industries of New York State/Business Council of New York State Records1996 December 19 - 2017 March 27
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Business Council Of New York State
apap043
10.02 cubic ft. processed to date 364 captures
The Associated Industries of New York State/ Business Council of New York State Records contains documents which were created during the group's 66 years of business. Among the contents are files on the group's former directors, correspondence and legal council records. The records of the association also contain some publications from other sources.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in the manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Business Council of New York State, Inc., on 30 June 1988.
Organizational Sketch
According to a short of history of the founding of Associated Industries of New York State, the Buffalo Chamber of Commerce called for a meeting of manufacturers on the 27th and the 28th of March 1914 in response to the labor laws of 1913 and 1914. Twenty-seven men, representing various businesses, met for these two days and appointed a committee to draft a constitution for an association which would combat legislation unfavorable to business. They voted unanimously in favor of that constitution, which gave the name of the organization as Federated Industries and its purpose as "to promote the mutual welfare of its members... and assist in establishing equitable and beneficial laws and rules pertaining to industries in the state of New York." The members decided their association should register as a corporation, and afterwards the executive committee met and voted to change the name of the association to Federated Industries, Inc., which was the first of many name changes.
By the executive committee meeting held on April 23, 1914, the association's name appeared in the general form it retained: Associated Industries (sometimes abbreviated to AI or AINY). An unincorporated body, the association determined in this first formal meeting "to go about its work not in a high-handed, but in a high-minded way, seeking to obtain only that to which it is entitled, but expecting to have all that willingly conceded and granted."
In the executive committee meeting of December 11, 1914, E. J. Barcalo, the first president of the association, brought up "the question of a proposed amalgamation between the New York State Manufacturers' Association and Associated Industries," but the members of Associated Industries worried that "the reported policy and the reputation of the New York State Manufacturers' Association as unfriendly to labor would be a detriment rather than an asset to Associated Industries."
At first, most of its members came from western New York, but by December 1914 the association had already begun to try to attract manufacturers in Glens Falls and were contemplating meeting with people in the Albany area. By 1915, the association had 748 members and a "considerable portion of the increase in membership was due to the amalgamation of Associated Industries and the New York State Manufacturers' Association, which occurred in June." The amalgamated association was named Associated Manufacturers and Merchants (of New York State). This merger helped extend the association's membership across the state. A few years later, the organization started to expand its membership into New York City.
During the board meeting of November 13, 1919, the board of directors recommended "the incorporation of the Association, under the Membership Corporations Law," and on January 29, 1920, Associated Industries of New York State, Inc., filed a certificate of incorporation.
The head office for Associated Industries opened in Buffalo in 1914. A second office opened in New York city in 1943 and another in Albany near the beginning of 1952. In late 1954, the New York office closed, and by 1962 the Buffalo office had closed, leaving the office in the state capital as the only office for the association.
The major officers of the association, the president and the secretary, were paid employees who did not have to be directors of the association. They and their assistants ran the daily business of Associated Industries. The executive committee made recommendations to the board of directors about all affairs of Associated Industries and required the approval of the board before acting on anything, but the executive committee also had the power to make decisions on its own in the interim between meetings.
On August 11, 1976, Active Industry for Development of the Economy (AIDE) was incorporated as a political action committee, funded by Associated Industries, that would donate money to political candidates "who will seek to improve the business climate of New York State." AIDE and a new policy of accepting whole associations as members to AI marked the beginning of a serious push to join others to achieve their goals.
The board of directors accepted Raymond T. Schuler as president on June 9, 1977. He was to be their last president. During Schuler's tenure, he built up staff positions, membership increased, and a few large companies like Gulf + Western and the Grumman Corporation joined AI. Schuler also travelled across the state making scores of speeches to business, fraternal and cultural groups.
According to a memorandum from the Empire State Chamber of Commerce and dated April 21, 1980, Associated Industries and Empire State Chamber of Commerce consolidated in 1980 to form The Business Council of New York State, Inc., with the goals of the new association being "to improve and promote the economy and business climate of New York State and promote the welfare of its members, their employees, consumers and the general public."
Scope and Contents
The general goal of Associated Industries was to restrict government involvement in business affairs, but the association had many specific interests, some of which changed or disappeared as the years progressed. One of their first and lasting concerns was workmen's compensation: they discussed and monitored legislation on this issue for the entire 66 years of their existence. Sometimes, though, their focus changed, as in the 1950's when their interest in workmen's compensation was especially concerned with occupational hearing loss. Taxation of all kinds, corporate as well as personal, always held their interest. Other topics of long term concern were unemployment insurance (1940-80), environmental pollution (ca. 1955-80), the cost and quality of education (1968-80), and energy policy (1971-80). There were also some subjects that interested for only a limited number of years. One of these was the National Bituminous Coal Act of 1937 which was an issue only until about 1945.
The primary sources of information about issues of concern for Associated Industries are the minutes of their board meetings (1914-79) and in The Monitor (1914-72), a monthly publication. During the 1960's, The Monitor became an organ of conservative opinion, even carrying a few articles by Ronald Reagan. Both these sources had information on the specific concerns of the association and on the general character of their thinking, but The Monitor is more frequently a source for their general political ideas and for their reactions to the events of their time because it was used as a public relations tool as well as a source of information for the association's members. After The Monitor ceased monthly publication and it became a quarterly leaflet named Monitor, the association published a few smaller publications which are not as good a source as the magazine these replaced. Press releases (1975-79) became a way for the association to disseminate their views and information about their activities. The issues files (1971-72, 1977-79) are not a very good source for information about the association's views because these files consist mostly of material not produced by Associated Industries.
During the term of president Raymond T. Schuler, there was a great increase in the amount of records produced. The most obvious of which was the addition of a president's file (1977-79) which consists of the scripts for speeches that Schuler made as president of Associated Industries and memoranda to and from the president's office. The speeches were an important part of the public relations of Associated Industries during the late 1970s.
The files on former directors (1950-81) contain files on individual directors which include correspondence from and concerning the directors, photographs of the directors, news clippings, tables of each director's association with Associated Industries, and other biographical material. For the most part, however, each individual file is fairly small and contains little information. Also within this series are general files on directors which are usually only lists of members of different committees.
The legal counsel records (1920, 1945-47, 1952-80) are not records produced by Associated Industries but are those kept by the different partners of Costello, Cooney & Fearon who served as legal counsel for the association. The bulk of these records consists of legal opinions as well as correspondence between Associated Industries and its legal counsel.
The records of the association also contain some publications from other sources (1957-80), most notably from Empire State Chamber of Commerce, an organization they eventually merged with to form The Business Council of New York State, Inc.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
All series are arranged chronologically with the exception of Series 4, subseries 2, which is arranged alphabetically.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Press Releases; Correspondence; Records and Briefs; Auditors' Reports; Publications; Albany (N.Y.); Administrative records; Minutes; Agendas; Web Archives; Wages -- New York (State); Associated Industries of New York State, inc.; Business Council of New York State
- Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetings Minutes, 1914-45., 1910-2010; Undated; 1; 2.2 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged chronologically and interfiled, except for the minutes of the Executive Committee meetings, 1915-19. Minutes through 1968 are glued into scrapbooks.
  Minutes of the meetings of the Board of Directors, including Associated Industries' first statement of purpose, various drafts of the constitution and by-laws (1914, 1920, 1955), and correspondence concerning the minutes (1923-62). Minutes of the meetings of the Executive Committee (1915-19, 1953-79).
  - Board of Directors, meeting minutes. Executive Committee, meeting minutes., ca. 1914-15 (Box 1 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee, meeting minutes., 1915-1919 (Box 1 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors, meeting minutes., 1915-1921; 1915; 1921 (Box 1 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors, meeting minutes., 1921-1925 (Box 1 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors, meeting minutes., 1925-1933 (Box 1 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors, meeting minutes., 1933-1945 (Box 1 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors, meeting minutes. Executive Committee, meeting minutes., 1945-1953; 1953 (Box 2 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meeting Minutes., 1953-1956 (Box 2 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meeting Minutes., 1956-1959 (Box 2 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meeting Minutes., 1959-1963 (Box 2 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meeting Minutes., 1963-1968 (Box 2 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meeting Minutes., 1968-1973 (Box 3 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meeting Minutes., 1973-1975 (Box 3 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meeting Minutes., 1980 (Box 3 (1-Board of Directors and Executive Committee, Meetin), Folder 4)
- Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meetings, Agenda., 1970-1979; 2; 1 cubic ft.
  Agenda distributed prior to the meetings, correspondence and memoranda concerning the meetings, pamphlets about the sites of large meetings, copies of minutes, copies of reports prepared for the meetings.
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1970 May 21 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1970 July 27 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1970 September 17 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1970 November 12 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1971 May 7 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1971 September 23 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1970 December 9 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1971 July 19 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 12)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1972 July 17 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1972 August 15 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 14)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1972 September 14 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 15)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1972 December 5 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1973 April 3 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 17-18)
  - Board of Directors Meeting., 1973 July 16 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1973 October 24 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 20)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1974 January 16 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 21)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1974 January 29 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 22)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1974 July 22 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 23)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1974 October 3 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 24)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1975 January 30 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 25-26)
  - Board of Directors Meeting (cancelled), 30-31 January 1970 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 27)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 21-22 July 1975 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 28-32)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1975 August 21 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 33-34)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1975 September 18 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 35-36)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1972 December 10 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 37-38)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1976 January 29 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 39-40)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1976 July 19 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 41-43)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1976 September 2 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 44-45)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1976 September 23 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 46-47)
  - Annual Membership Meeting., 1976 September 24 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 48)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1976 October 28 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 49-50)
  - Special Board Meeting on Revised Constitution and By-Laws., 1977 January 27 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 51)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1977 January 27 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 52-53)
  - Board of Directors Meeting., 1977 June 9 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 54)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1977 July 24-25 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 55-57)
  - Board of Directors Meeting (Folder 1)., 1977 September 25 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 58)
  - Board of Directors Meeting (Folder 2)., 1977 September 25 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 59)
  - Executive Committee Meeting., 1977 October 7 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 60)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1978 January 24 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 61-63)
  - Executive Committee Meeting (Conference Telephone Call), 1978 March 17 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 64)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1978 May 18 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 65-66)
  - Board of Directors and Nominating Committee Meetings, 1978 July 24-25 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 67-68)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1978 July 25 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 69)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1978 September 14 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 70-71)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, 1979 January 16 (Box 3 (2-Board of Directors and Executive Committee Meeting), Folder 72-73)
- President's Files, 1977-1979; 3; 1.14 cubic ft.
  Speech files contain drafts of the speeches of AINY president, Raymond T. Schuler, correspondence concerning the speeches, programs for some of the events at which Schuler gave a speech, and news clippings concerning the subjects of the speeches.
  Memorandum files contain memoranda from the president Raymond T. Schuler (and occasionally from others) to the members of the Board of Directors and the Executive Committee.
  - Speech to the Greater Buffalo Chamber of Commerce (GBC), 1977 September 8 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 1)
  - Speech Before the Senate Standing Committee on Labor, 1977 September 15 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 2)
  - Speech at Lockport, 1977 September 20 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 3)
  - Speech to the Bankers Association, 1977 September 28 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 4)
  - Speech at Syracuse, 1977 September 30 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 5)
  - Speech to the Rotary Club of Armonk, NY, 1977 October 4 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 6)
  - Speech to the Westchester County Association, 1977 October 4 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 7)
  - Speech to the Oneida Chamber of Commerce, 1977 October 8 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 8)
  - Speech at Corning, 1977 October 12 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 9)
  - Speech at Ulster County Community College, 1977 October 13 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 10)
  - Statement on the Westchester Growth Phenomenon, 1977 October (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 11)
  - Speech at Industry/Environmental Conference, 1977 November 1 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 12)
  - Speech to Members of the Oneida County Chamber of Commerce, 1977 November 2 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 13)
  - Speech at Fishkill, 1977 November 10 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 14)
  - Speech Before the Senate Subcommittee on the Impact of Taxes on Small Businesses, 1977 November 15 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 15)
  - Speech to the Tripartite Conference, 1977 November 16 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 16)
  - Speech to Public Administrators, 1977 November 29 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 17)
  - Speech to Colonie Chamber of Commerce, 1977 November 29 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 18)
  - Speech to the League of Women Voters, 1977 November 30 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 19)
  - Speech to the New York State Motor Truck Association, 1977 December 6 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 20)
  - Speech to Self-Insurers, 1977 December 7 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 21)
  - Speech Before the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, 1977 December 8 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 22)
  - Speech to New York Bankers, 1977 December 14 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 23)
  - Speech at Cornell, 1978 January 10 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 24)
  - Speech to Syracuse Transportation Club, 1978 January 19 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 25)
  - Speech to the Industrial Forum of Erie County, 1978 February 2 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 26)
  - Speech to the Jamestown Manufacturers Association, 1978 February 7 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 27)
  - Speech to the Latham Kiwanis, 1978 February 23 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 28)
  - Speech to the Buffalo Chamber of Commerce, 1978 February 28 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 29)
  - Speech to the Industrial Management Council of Rochester, 1978 February 28 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 30)
  - Speech to the AFL-CIO, 1978 March 8 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 31)
  - Speech to the Niagara Frontier Group, 1978 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 32)
  - Speech at State University of New York, Albany, 1978 April 4 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 33)
  - Speech at Stony Brook, 1978 April 5 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 34)
  - Speech to Bankers for the Expansion of New York's Economy (B.E.N.Y.E.), 1978 April 6 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 35)
  - Speech to Union Carbide, 1978 April 10 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 36)
  - Speech to the Industrial Relations Association of Western New York, 1978 April 11 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 37)
  - Speech at Rockland County Annual Dinner, 1978 May 5 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 38)
  - Speech to the Troy Chamber of Commerce, 1978 May 23 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 39)
  - Speech to Bankers, 1978 June 5 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 40)
  - Speech on Economic Development Planning, 1978 June 12 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 41)
  - Speech at Cornell on Industrial/Labor Relations, 1978 June 16 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 42)
  - Speech to Associated Industries, Board of Directors Meeting, 1978 July 25 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 43)
  - Speech to the Energy Conference--Plenary Session, 1978 September 20 (Box 4 (3-President's Files), Folder 44)